Guide to the Walter Thorn Papers BCMS.0076
Brooklyn Collection
Walter Thorn Papers
1861-1919
1898-1910
Brooklyn Collection
Thorn, Walter, 1844-1920
BCMS.0076
0.4 Linear feet in 1 document box
Letters, documents, news clippings and related personal papers of Walter Thorn (1844-1920), a Brooklyn civic leader and attorney who served in the Civil War.
Biographical Note
Walter Thorn was an attorney, prominent Brooklyn resident, and outspoken abolitionist who served in the Union army during the United States Civil War. He served in two New York Infantry units before becoming second lieutenant in the 116th Infantry, a regiment of Black soldiers from Kentucky. In the 116th he attained the rank of Brevet Major and won several medals for combat and bravery.
After the war, Thorn held several government posts at the federal, county, and local levels. He was Captain of the New York National Guard and active in veterans' organizations. He was appointed a Deputy Sheriff in Brooklyn as well as to other local government posts. In the early 1900s, he served as commander of the Medal of Honor Legion and President of the War Veterans and Sons Association.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes correspondence, documents, news clippings, a small autograph collection, ephemera, bound reports of the Medal of Honor Legion Annual Convention, and one photograph. The materials in this collection date primarily to the years following the Civil War with a focus on Thorn's civic activities, especially with the Medal of Honor Legion. The 12 autographs in this collection are from Civil War officers and other prominent friends, including 27th Vice President James S. Sherman and Civil War Major General Henry Ware Lawton, a fellow Medal of Honor winner killed during the Philippine-American War.
Provenance
Purchased from Between the Covers Rare Books in 2019.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series: Series I: Correspondence, Series II: Documents, Series III: Autographs, Ephemera and Photograph and Series IV: Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbook. Series I and Series II are arranged chronologically. Series III is arranged by type, and the autographs are arranged alphabetically. The newspaper clippings in Series V are grouped to match their original arrangement in four folders and a scrapbook. The clippings have been photocopied for preservation. The small amount of non-clipping ephemera from the scrapbook is foldered separately.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Newsstand: Many of the clippings in this collection come from Brooklyn newspapers that are available digitally in this database.
Brooklyn in the Civil War website
Letters of James W. Vanderhoef: A collection of letters written by Civil War soldier James W. Vanderhoef.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Medal of Honor; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Medal of Honor Legion letters, circa 1899-1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brooklyn Daily Times letter, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Documents
  - Appointments certificates, 1870-1873 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Medal of Honor Legion Annual Convention Reports, 1902-1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Surgeon Gabriel Grant memorial tribute, circa 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series III: Autographs, Ephemera and Photograph
  - Autographs, circa 1864-1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    General
    Childs, George W. Publisher and philanthropist.
    Creswell, John A.J. Maryland Congressman and Senator and Postmaster General under President Grant.
    Dickinson, Donald M. Postmaster General under President Cleveland.
    Eckert, Thomas T. Brigadier General in the Civil War, Assistant Secretary of War (1865-67) and Western Union executive.
    Haldane, Richard B. British politician, lawyer, and philosopher.
    James, Thomas L. Journalist, banker, and Postmaster General under President Garfield.
    Lawton, Henry Ware. Major General in the Civil War and Medal of Honor winner.
    Schenk, Robert C. Major General in the Civil War and diplomat.
    Sherman, James S. 27th Vice President of the United States (1909-1912).
    Unidentified. "Union General Civil War" in ink on verso.
  - Ephemera, 1881-1901 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - South Carolina National Guard photograph, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbook
  - G.A.R. [Grand Army of the Republic] clippings, circa 1880s-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - War Vets & Sons clippings, circa 1897-1902 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - War Veterans and Sons Association clippings, circa 1897-1914 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mixed clippings, circa 1875-1912 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook clippings, circa 1898-1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook ephemera, circa 1861-1912 (Box 1, Folder 14)